Leopold Stokowski Papers, 1916-1994 PUSp.Ms. Coll. 381
University of Pennsylvania: Rare Book Manuscript Library
Eugene Ormandy invited Stokowski to return to Philadelphia in January 1959 to guest conduct the Philadelphia Orchestra. Stokowski performed Mozart's Overture to The Marriage of Figaro; Falla's El amor brujo, with Shirley Verrett as soloist; Respighi's The Pines of Rome; and Shostakovich's Symphony no. 5 to an enthusiastic standing ovation as Philadelphians welcomed him back after nearly twenty years absence.
Following the sudden death of Dimitri Mitropoulous in November 1960, Rudolf Bing of the Metropolitan Opera invited Leopold Stokowski to conduct the Opera's upcoming performance of Puccini's Turandot, scheduled for 24 February 1961. A few days before the end of December, Stokowski fell and broke his hip while playing with his boys. Although he was in pain during rehearsals and used crutches to enter the orchestra pit, his performance of Turandot was highly praised by the critics. The Met brought Turandot to Philadelphia on March 22 for a performance at Philadelphia's Metropolitan Opera House. Stokowski opened the 1961 Edinburgh Festival in August with a performance of Schoenberg's Gurrelieder with the London Symphony Orchestra and the Edinburgh Royal Choral Union. Leopold Stokowski founded the American Symphony Orchestra in New York City in 1962. Again, as he had done with the All-American Youth Orchestra, Stokowski auditioned and hired young musicians, many of them women and minorities, to play with a few seasoned hands. Stokowski conducted this orchestra without pay and made some of its deficits up out of his own pocket. In 1965 Stokowski succeeded in fulfilling a long-held desire B to give the world premier of Charles Ives' Symphony no. 4 with the American Symphony Orchestra. Stokowski was 83 years old; he rehearsed the symphony for two months with special funding from the Rockefeller Foundation. The performance, with three conductors, was a landmark. Stokowski recorded the symphony shortly thereafter.
On 1 May 1972, a few weeks after Stokowski had celebrated his 90th birthday, Stokowski submitted his resignation to the Board of Directors of the American Symphony Orchestra. Stokowski had made plans to move to England where he had contacts in the recording industry at London-Decca and where he could continue to guest conduct the London Symphony Orchestra. He bought an old farmhouse in Nether Wallop and made plans for its renovations. Stokowski conducted New Philarmonia in 1974 which was to be his last performance for the public in England. He continued to make recordings. In 1975 he was in the process of building a house near St. Paul de Vence on the Riviera in France, which Stokowski named Con Brio. There he met Marc Chagall and admired Matisse's chapel. The house was completed in 1976 and Stokowski spent time in France whenever he was not working on recordings in England.
Stokowski died at his home in Nether Wallop, Stockbridge, Hampshire on 13 September 1977 at the age of 95 years. He had made more than twenty recordings since his 90th birthday and was studying the Rachmaninoff Symphony No. 2 in preparation for a recording session at the time of his death. Stokowski was buried in a private ceremony in the Marylebone Cemetery in London. His friend and admirer former Prime Minister Edward Heath delivered the eulogy.
This brief sketch of Leopold Stokowski's life cannot possibly cover all the significant events and contributions he made to music in the twentieth century. Stokowski had a strong desire to make great music accessible to people in all walks of life and welcomed developments in recording technology, film, radio, and television which made this possible. In 1943 he published a book titled Music for All of Us in which he tried to introduce both his technical and spiritual understanding of music to the public. In an interview with Robert Dumm in New York while Stokowski was conductor of the Houston Symphony Orchestra, Stokowski said, My idea of conducting is something very simple. It is to try by every means possible to convey from the composer... his inspiration, the beauty of his music, the meaning of his music, the dynamic of his music, or perhaps sometimes the mystery of his music to the listener. And, we, the orchestra in between...we're merely means to an end. We=re like an electric wire that runs from one place to another and conveys electricity to a lamp, we might say, to give light.
- Correspondence, I
  Series Description
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent, then chronologically within each folder or series of folders. Items of incoming and outgoing correspondence are interfiled.
  - Leopold Stokowski Correspondence, A
    - Adler, Larry - Guy Price Company (Box 1, Folder 1-71)
    - Habenicht, Walter - Musser, Claire Omar (Box 2, Folder 72-124)
    - N. V. Sprenger - Young, Barbara (Box 3, Folder 125-198)
  - Curtis Institute of Music Administrative Correspondence, 1980-1995; B
    Description
    Correspondence generated between 1980 and 1995 related to the Leopold Stokowski Collection. The principal correspondent at Curtis was the curator of the collection, Dr. Edwin E. Heilakka. A copy of the contract of assignment of the scores to Curtis and the Curtis inventory of the collection is filed at the end of this series.
    - Correspondence, A-K (Box 4, Folder 199-250)
    - Correspondence, L-W (Box 5, Folder 251-296)
    - Confirmatory Assignment, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 297-298)
    - Catalog of Stokowski collection (Box 5, Folder 299)
    - Events, memorabilia, notes about the Stokowski collection (Box 5, Folder 300)
- Leopold Stokowski notes, audition materials, and calendars, II
  - Notes laid in music scores, A
    Arrangement
    Arranged alphabetically by composer and title of the score.
    - Bach-Mussorgsky (Box 6, Folder 301-326)
    - Orff-Wagner (Box 7, Folder 327-350)
  - Notebooks, notes, and receipts, 1937-1944; B
    Arranged by subject.
    - Notes on music and musicians, 1
      - Notebook, loose-leaf, 1930s-1941 (Box 8, Folder 351-352)
        Comprises typed form letters from Stokowski, annotated in his hand. Includes letters to composers, letters regarding auditions, letters regarding the All-American Youth Orchestra, letters of regret, etc.
      - Notes regarding electric orchestra, includes a few sketches, undated (Box 8, Folder 353-354)
      - Notes on Hollywood musicians and orchestra, undated (Box 8, Folder 355)
      - Notes on Hollywood Committee for Polish Relief, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 356)
      - List of Stokowski's music library, undated (Box 8, Folder 357)
      - Notes and sketch for the Temple of Music (planned for Philadelphia), undated (Box 8, Folder 358)
    - Household management, 2
      Notes, correspondence, and receipts for household management regarding employees, purchases, gardening, utilities, and travel.
      - Notes, correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 9, Folder 359)
      - Notes, correspondence, 1939-1940 (Box 9, Folder 360)
      - Notes, correspondence, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 361)
      - Notes, re garden, undated (Box 9, Folder 362)
      - Receipts, household, misc., 1939-1945 (Box 9, Folder 363)
      - Receipts, garden, 1937-1944 (Box 9, Folder 364)
      - Beverly Hills City Directory, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 365)
      - Travel pamphlets and notes (Box 9, Folder 366-367)
  - Audition notebook, C
    Musical selections played at auditions.
    - Audition notebook, undated (Box 10)
      Arranged by orchestra parts, with Stokowski's comments on and rating of each musician, loose leaf sheets have been placed in mylar for preservation.
    - Original loose-leaf binder for this audition notebook, repaired with tape, ASO on spine (Box 11)
    - Folder of manuscript music to be played for Stokowski for auditions, Auditions on cover (Box 12)
  - Leopold Stokowski calendars, 1956-February 1962; D
    - Hand ruled and decorated notebooks (Box 13)
      Includes his entries on meetings, rehearsals, visits with his children, birthdays, holidays, etc.
- Leopold Stokowski legal, insurance, and financial records, III
  - Correspondence with attorney Joseph Sharfsin, A
    - Correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box 14, Folder 368-369)
      Re Stokowski's plans to register a trademark for COLORHYTHM; Stokowski's will; Stokowski's divorce settlement with Evangeline Johnson; and his planned trip to South America (1940).
    - Paul Stuart Buchanan vs. Leopold Stokowski, Los Angeles County Superior Court, re deposition, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 370)
  - Contracts, B
    - Agreement between Theodore Presser Company, Carl Fischer, Inc., Edward W. Bok and Leopold Stokowski, re Stokowski's composition Our United States, 1925 (Box 14, Folder 371)
    - Victor Talking Machine Company recording contracts, 1929-1930 (Box 14, Folder 372)
    - Radio Corporation of America recording contract, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 373)
    - Radio Corporation of America extensions of contract and agreements, 1937-1940 (Box 14, Folder 374)
    - Contract draft re concert management for Electric Symphony Orchestra concerts at the San Francisco World's Fair, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 375)
  - Royalty statements and bank statements, C
    - Leopold Stokowski accounts, 1
      - Mechanical-Copyright Protection Society Limited royalty statements, 1938-1940 (Box 14, Folder 376)
      - Bank of America deposit/debit slips, 1938-1944 (Box 14, Folder 377)
      - Bank of America statements of account, 1943-1945 (Box 14, Folder 378)
      - Bankers Trust Company statements of account, 1943-1944 (Box 14, Folder 379)
      - Central Hanover Bank and Trust correspondence, deposit/debit slips, 1942-1945 (Box 14, Folder 380)
      - Central Hanover Bank and Trust statements of account, 1943-1944 (Box 14, Folder 381)
      - Chase National Bank correspondence, deposit/debit slips (Box 14, Folder 382)
      - Chase National Bank statements of accounts, 1943-1945 (Box 14, Folder 383-385)
      - E. F. Hutton Company, 1937-1944 (Box 14, Folder 386)
      - First National Bank (Philadelphia, Pa.) correspondence, deposit/debit slips, 1938-1941 (Box 14, Folder 387)
      - Hartford National Bank Trust Co. statements of account, 1945-1946 (Box 14, Folder 388)
      - Philadelphia National Bank blank check (Box 14, Folder 389)
      - Provident Trust Company of Philadelphia correspondence, 1937-1938 (Box 14, Folder 390)
      - Security-First National Bank of Los Angeles statement of account, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 391)
    - Luba and Sadja Stokowski accounts, 2
      - Central Hanover Bank and Trust statements of accounts and Stokowski's notes re maintenance funds, 1942-1944 (Box 14, Folder 392-395)
      - Scarborough School catalog with notes regarding Sadja, 1941-1942 (Box 14, Folder 396)
  - Financial notes, petty cash accounts, income tax (employer's forms), D
    - Petty cash account book, not bound; petty cash slips, 1938-1939 (Box 14, Folder 397-398)
    - Miscellaneous financial notes, 1938-1944 (Box 14, Folder 399)
    - Income tax employer's forms, 1942-1944 (Box 14, Folder 400-402)
  - Checkbooks and check stubs, E
    - First National Bank Philadelphia, 1933-1940 (Box 15, Folder 403)
    - Bank of America. Hollywood, Calif., 1938-1940 (Box 15, Folder 404)
    - Bank of America. Hollywood, Calif., 1940-1941 (Box 15, Folder 405)
  - Insurance correspondence and policies, F
    - Correspondence re automobile insurance, personal property insurance, workmen's compensation policies, 1936-1941 (Box 16, Folder 406-410)
    - Insurance policies, 1938-1941 (Box 16, Folder 411)
- Writings and interview transcripts by and about Leopold Stokowski, IV
  - Writings by Stokowski, A
    - Stokowski, Leopold. An Interpretation of Modern Music, in Arts and Decoration, 1922 November (Box 17, Folder 412)
    - Stokowski, Leopold. Narration for London Records re Beethoven, Symphony no. 9, typescript (Box 17, Folder 413)
    - Stokowski, Leopold. The Seating of the Orchestra, in Forum, 1972 Spring (Box 17, Folder 414)
    - Stokowski, Leopold. Music and Electronics, undated (Box 17, Folder 415)
  - Writings about Stokowski, B
    This is not a comprehensive collection of writings about Stokowski, however the series of writings by William Ander Smith, who contributed his essay on Stokowski to American National Biography, is reliable.
    - Biographical sketches and notes (Box 17, Folder 416)
    - Academy of Music (Philadelphia, Pa.). 115th Anniversary Concert and Ball. Souvenir program, 1972 (Box 17, Folder 417)
    - Biswanger, Ray. The Stokowski-Wanamaker Concerts typescript, and The Story of the Wanamaker Organs, in American Organist 22(9) 50-64 with photocopies of succeeding issues, parts 2 and 3, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 418-420)
    - Columbia Records. Leopold Stokowski, biographical sketch, circa 1976 (Box 17, Folder 421)
    - Cooke, Hereward Lester. Acoustical Control of Theatre Design, Journal of the Franklin Institute 208, no. 3, 1929 (Box 17, Folder 422)
      This item was found in Stokowski's papers in Beverly Hills, California.
    - Heilakka, Edwin E. The Leopold Stokowski Collection at The Curtis Institute of Music, in WFLN Philadelphia Guide, List of transcriptions by Leopold Stokowski, typescript, 1982 April (Box 17, Folder 423)
    - Johnson, Edward. Leopold Stokowski: Off the Record, a compilation of record reviews (Box 17, Folder 424)
    - Johnson, Edward, ed. Stokowski: Essays in Analysis of his Art, 1973; 2 copies (Box 17, Folder 425-426)
    - Knight, John. Leopold Stokowski Explores Debussy's Orchestral Colors, Instrumentalist 50, no. 9, 1996 April (Box 17, Folder 427)
    - Krell, John C. The 1941 Stokowski All-American Youth Tour, typescript (Box 17, Folder 428)
    - Marks, Robert W. Orient Colors Stokowski's Vista, Musical America and Eyer, Ronald F. The Philadelphia Orchestra, Musical America, 1928 September 15, 1937 January 25 (Box 17, Folder 429)
    - Ovation. Leopold Stokowski Centenary Tribute, 1982 April (Box 17, Folder 430)
    - Pogue, Samuel F. Some Unpublished Letters of Stokowski, Notes 46, no. 1, 1989 September (Box 17, Folder 431)
      Quarterly Journal of the Music Library Association, re letters at the University of Cincinnati Libraries.
    - RCA Victor. Stokowski and the Philadelphia Orchestra Promotional booklet, circa 1932 (Box 17, Folder 432)
    - Robinson, Paul. Stokowski with discography by Bruce Surtees. Lester and Orpen Limited, photocopy (discography only) (Box 17, Folder 433)
    - Smith, William Ander. Stokowski at One Hundred, South Atlantic Quarterly 81:3, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 434)
    - Smith, William Ander. Leopold Stokowski: A Re-evaluation, American Music, 1983 Fall (Box 17, Folder 435)
    - Smith, William Ander. Leopold Stokowski, drafts and final copy of biographical essay for American National Biography, 1990, undated (Box 17, Folder 436)
    - Stokowski: The Philadelphia Years, The Morton C. Grad Collection, undated (Box 17, Folder 437)
      Tape programs and index.
    - Walt Disney Productions. Fantasia. Story meetings, 1938 September (Box 17, Folder 438)
    - Review of Stokowski's Band of Gold, unidentified, undated (Box 17, Folder 439)
    - Review of Darius Milhaud conducting the Philadelphia Orchestra, typescript, unidentified (mentions Stokowski), undated (Box 17, Folder 440)
  - Ruth O'Neill -Samuel Rosenbaum materials, C
    Interview transcripts and related items. Ruth O'Neill was a secretary to Arthur Judson when he was manager of the Philadelphia Orchestra and was also secretary to Leopold Stokowski. These interviews were conducted in 1972 in order to document Arthur Judson's contributions to music over his long career. Samuel R. Rosenbaum was a member of the Board of Directors of the Philadelphia Orchestra for many years. Leopold Stokowski and Olga Samaroff Stokowski are mentioned in these interviews.
    - Leinsdorf, Erich to Ruth O'Neill, from Leinsdort congratulating O'Neill on becoming partner [with Arthur Judson], 1947 December 15 (Box 18, Folder 441)
    - Transcript of tape recording of luncheon meeting at the St. Moritz Hotel, New York, N.Y., 1972 January 6 (Box 17, Folder 442)
      With the following: Arthur Judson, Ruth O'Neill, Samuel R. Rosenbaum, and John J. Buckley.
    - Transcript of tape recording of luncheon meeting in New York, N.Y., 1972 March 8 (Box 18, Folder 443)
    - Transcript of interview with Ruth O'Neill and Samuel R. Rosenbaum re Arthur Judson, 1972 May 17 (Box 18, Folder 444)
    - Transcript of interview with Ruth O'Neill, Arthur Judson, Samuel R. Rosenbaum, and John J. Buckley, undated (Box 18, Folder 445)
    - Transcript of interview with Ruth O'Neill, Arthur Judson, and Samuel R. Rosenbaum, circa 1972 April (Box 18, Folder 446)
    - Transcript of interview with Samuel R. Rosenbaum and Ruth O'Neill in Miss O'Neill's apartment, undated (Box 18, Folder 447)
    - Rosenbaum, Samuel R. Henry S. Drinker, An Amateur of Music, with Amateurs and Muisc an address by Henry S. Drinker, 1958, 1935 (Box 18, Folder 448)
- Serials, V
  Arranged chronologically and includes the following serials:
  A. Youth, 1935, undated. Magazine of the Philadelphia Youth Movement, also called Youth Music Magazine, written by and for members of the Youth Concert series and Youth Choruses, founded by Leopold Stokowski in 1932-1933.
  B. Toccata. Bulletin of The Leopold Stokowski Society. Founded in 1978 in England, the objects of the Society are to perpetuate and promote interest in the conductor's work; to ensure that his work will continue to be available for study by future music lovers; and to promote the re-issue of the conductor's recorded performances.
  C. Maestrino. Journal of The Leopold Stokowski Society of America. Founded in September 1983. First published in Spring 1984 (mailed June 1984). Not a complete run of all issues.
  - Youth, v. 1-v. 3, 1935 April-October (Box 19, Folder 449-450)
  - Toccata, Bulletin no. 2, 1979 March-April - 1981 May-June (Box 19, Folder 451)
  - Toccata, Bulletin no. 1, 1979 January - 1982-1983 Winter (Box 19, Folder 452-473)
  - Toccata, not complete, 1983 Spring - 1998 Winter (Box 20, Folder 474-502)
  - Maestrino, not complete, 1984 June - 1993 Summer (Box 21, Folder 503-511)
- Programs, VI
  - Leopold Stokowski programs, 1916-1974; A
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Programs, 1916 March 2 - 1939 April 8 (Box 22, Folder 512-576)
      Stokowski conducting the Philadelphia Orchestra, the Philadelphia Civic Opera Company, and Philadelphia Grand Opera Company.
    - Programs, 1940 March 21 - 1974 May 14 (Box 23, Folder 577-630)
      Stokowski conducting the Philadelphia Orchestra, the All-American Youth Orchestra, the New York Philharmonic, the NBC Symphony Orchestra, the New York City Symphony, the Hollywood Bowl Symphony Orchestra, the American Composers' Alliance concert, the London Symphony Orchestra, the American Symphony Orchestra, the Boston Symphony Orchestra, the Royal Philharmonic Orchestra and the New Philharomonia.
  - Performances of Leopold Stokowski's transcriptions, B
    Arranged alphabetically by the name of the orchestra performing the transcriptions.
    - Orchestras, A-G (Box 24, Folder 631-652)
    - Orchestras, I-O (Box 25, Folder 653-668)
    - Orchestras, P-T (Box 26, Folder 669-686)
- Photographs, albums, and scrapbooks, VII
  - Photographs of Stokowski, 1912-1982; A
    Arranged chronologically. For additional photographs of Leopold Stokowski, see Oversize Box 41 and Oversize Map Drawer 61. Photographs of Stokowski and his associates used as illustrations in Oliver Daniel's biography are located in his research collection, Ms. Coll. 382, Boxes 48 and 49.
    - 1912-1950 (Box 27)
    - 1953-1977 (Box 28)
      Plus photographs of 1982 Centenary celebrations.
    - Stokowski, Leopold, and Evangeline Johnson, circa 1927-1928 (Box 29)
      Scrapbook and photograph album. Some items annotated in Stokowski's hand documenting the Stokowskis' world-wide trip? 2 photographs plus memorabilia. Incomplete album, rehoused for preservation.
  - Other photographs, B
    - Curtis Institute of Music, 1982 (Box 30)
      Stokowski Centennial Celebration. Color and b w photographs, proof sheets, negatives.
    - Curtis Institute of Music. Leopold Stokowski Collection (Box 31)
      Album compiled by curator Edwin E. Heilakka.. Depicts items in the collection, scores, musical instruments, etc. and events, including the 1982 Stokowski Centennial Celebration.
    - Stolwein, Sue. Photograph and autograph album, 1923-1964, undated (Box 32)
      Celebrities who visited the Russian Inn, Philadelphia [?]. Donor unknown. Date of last inscription to Stolwein is 1951, other photographs may have been added later. It is not clear what the relationship of this album is to other items in the collection, may have contained Stokowski photographs which were integrated into the collection.
  - Scrapbooks, C
    - All-American Youth Orchestra, 1941 (Box 33)
      Photocopied clippings and memorabilia.
    - Edinburgh International Festival, 1961 (Box 34)
      Scrapbook and photo album compiled by Preben and Mimi Opperby in commemoration of Stokowski's performance of Schoenberg's Gurrelieder.in 1961. Dedicated to Leopold Stokowski.
    - Hollywood Bowl Summer '72, 50th Birthday Superseason, circa 1972-1984 (Box 34)
      Compiled by Gustav S. Jánossy. Clippings, programs, [most are photocopies]; a few items on Stokowski, most are on the history of all performances at the Hollywood Bowl.
- Awards and artwork, VIII
  - Awards, A
    - Philadelphia Award, 1922 (Box 35)
      Ivory and rosewood box, designed by Violet Oakley; executed by Douglas Gilchrist, plaque on bottom with date, 1922. Designed to hold the medal, (designed by Oakley) and scroll (painted by Violet Oakley) [scroll is stored separately in Drawer 61]. Letter from Edwin Heilakka to the Philadelphia Award Trustees, 7 March 1988, indicates that The medal is in the possession of a daughter, and is, I understand, to be presented to the [Stokowski] Collection in due course.
    - Prix mondial du disque de Montreux, undated (Box 36)
      Pewter drinking vessel.
    - Philadelphia Orchestra, 1966 (Box 36)
      Silver plaque mounted on mineral specimen reads Leopold Stowkowski [sic] in honor of one of the great moments of the Philadelphia Orchestra with deepest gratitude. The members of the Philadelphia Orchestra, Convention Hall, October 14, 1966.
    - Medals and awards (Box 37)
      Contents
      * New York, N.Y. George Friderick Handel Award. Presented by Mayor Robert F. Wagner, April 15, 1963. Charlotte Tremper Armus, sculptor, 1959. Bronze medal in black leather case.
      * Antonin Dvorak medal, undated. Mil.Beutler, sculptor. Bronze medal in rose leather case.
      * American Council for Nationalities Service. Golden Door Award, 1966. Gold-plated medal in black leather case.
      * Anton Weber medal, 1967. Siv Holme, sculptor. Bronze medal in blue cardboard box.
      * Claude Debussy medal, 1978. R. Joly, sculptor. Bronze medal in blue cardboard box.
      * Heitor Villa-Lobos medal, undated. No box. This medal was given to Stokowski in 1975 by Arminda Villa-Lobos (see correspondence in Oliver Daniel collection 3 March 1975).
    - National Academy of Recording Arts and Sciences, 1967 (Box 38)
      Nomination for the Album of the Year-Classical. The World of Charles Ives. To Leopold Stokowski and to Leonard Bernstein. Plaque.
    - Philadelphia Music Foundation Award, undated (Box 38)
      Base, black marble, with treble clef. [Stored in two pieces].
  - Artwork, B
    Note
    See also: Bloch, Julius. Stokowski, lithograph, Oversize drawer 61.
    - Fisher, Albert. Watercolor portrait of Leopold Stokowski conducting, 25 x 25 cm., undated (Box 39, Folder 687)
    - Kairer, Margaret G. Pencil sketch of Leopold Stokowski conducting with his daughter Sonya at his side, 18.5 x13.5 cm., 1925 (Box 39, Folder 688)